Guide to the William Sawitzky Research Notes 1926-1975 MS 0540
New-York Historical Society
William Sawitzky research notes
1926-1975
New-York Historical Society
Sawitzky, William, 1879 or 1880-1947
MS 0540
70 Linear feet in 143 boxes
This collection consists of the research notes, manuscripts, typescripts, photostats, photographs, lectures, correspondence, and graphic materials of art historian William Sawitzky (1879-1947). Most of the material dates from l930-1947, and documents Sawitzky's extensive research on early American art and artists, including Ralph Earl, Matthew Pratt, and Gilbert Stuart. Later material is the work of his wife, Susan Clay Sawitzky (1897-1981).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 5 series by subject:
Series I: Art Lectures
Series II: Artists
Series III: Correspondence
Series IV: Published Volumes
Series V: Miscellaneous
Biographical / Historical
William Sawitzky (1879-1947) was an authority on early American portraiture who served as Advisory Curator of American Art at the New-York Historical Society from 1940 until his death in 1947.
Born in Riga, Russia, Sawitzky studied art history and biology and began his career as an ornithological field worker in the Ural Mountains. He then worked as a journalist in Riga, and came to the United States in 1911 as a special correspondent covering art and literature.
Sawitzky became the art librarian at the Knoedler Gallery in 1913, where he began to take an interest in early American painting. Some of the many artists he studied include Matthew Pratt, Ralph Earl, and Gilbert Stuart.
He left Knoedler in 1920 and spent the next decade doing field work and arranging exhibitions of American paintings at museums, art societies, and clubs in many Midwestern and Southern U.S. cities, and studying paintings in Europe. During this period, Sawitzky edited the four-volume edition of Lawrence Park's work on the painter Gilbert Stuart for the Frick Art Reference Library, published in 1926. He married Susan Clay (1897-1981) in 1927, and she became a partner in his research.
Beginning in 1930, Sawitzky traveled throughout New England, New York, Pennsylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North and South Carolina, Kentucky, Tennessee, Alabama and Louisiana, conducting an extensive survey of thousands of early American paintings and miniatures.
In 1940, under a grant from the Carnegie Corporation, Sawitzky became the Advisory Curator for American Art at the New-York Historical Society and Lecturer on Fine Arts at New York University. During his tenure, he gave a series of lectures based on his extensive research identifying previously little-known early American artists, and on correcting erroneous attributions of artworks.
Sources:
New York Historical Society Quarterly, v.25, January 1941
New York Historical Society Quarterly, v.31, April 1947
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift, unknown donor, possibly Susan Clay Sawitzky, circa 1981.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of the research notes, manuscripts, typescripts, photostats, photographs, lectures, correspondence, books, and graphic material of American art historian William Sawitzky (1879-1947). Sawitzky's area of expertise was early American art and artists, particularly portraits. His extensive research focused on identifying previously little-known artists, and on correcting erroneous attributions of artworks. Some of the many artists he studied include Matthew Pratt, Ralph Earl, and Gilbert Stuart. Material in this collection dated after 1947 is the work of William Sawitzky's wife, Susan Clay Sawitzky (1897-1981).
Of particular interest are the transcripts of a series of lectures Sawitzky gave while serving as Advisory Curator of American Art at the New-York Historical Society. Organized in conjuction with New York University between 1940-1942, the lectures were the products of Sawitsky's decades of fieldwork and research in early American art. The transcripts are based on notes taken by Susan Clay Sawitzky at these lectures.
Related Materials
Correspondence with William Sawitzky and Susan Clay Sawitzky can also be found in three record groups of N-YHS's institutional archives: Publication Editorial Records (NYHS-RG 17), General Correspondence (NYHS-RG 2), and, to a lesser extent, Librarian Dorothy C. Barck records (NYHS-RG 19).
Art, American.; Art historians -- United States.; Art -- History.; Painters -- United States.; Research notes.; Sawitzky, Susan Clay, 1897-1981; Earl, Ralph, 1751-1801; Pratt, Matthew, 1734-1805; Stuart, Gilbert, 1755-1828; New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Art Lectures, 1940-1942
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the notes, slides, and transcripts related to Sawitzky's lectures on early American art. The lectures were given at the New-York Historical Society between 1940-1942.
  - Notes for lectures, 1940-1942 (Offsite-box 165, Box 63)
  - Notes for lectures, 1940-1942 (Offsite-box 166, Box 64)
  - Notes for lectures, 1940-1942 (Offsite-box 166, Box 65)
  - Slides for lectures, September 1940-October 1941 (Offsite-box 167, Box 66)
  - Slides for lectures, September 1940-October 1941 (Offsite-box 167, Box 67)
  - Slides for lectures, October 1941-January 1942 (Offsite-box 172, Box 80)
  - Transcripts of lectures, 1940-1942 (Offsite-box 135)
    30 volumes
- Series II: Art and Artists, 1930-1960
  This series, which comprises the bulk of the collection, contains the research notes and other material that documents Sawitzky's fieldwork and study of early American artists, as well as some of their European counterparts.
  - Art Collections, Clarke-Mellon Collection, 1930-1940 (Offsite-box 183, Box 111)
  - Art Collections, Clarke-Mellon Collection, 1930-1940 (Offsite-box 183, Box 112)
  - Art Collections by geographic area, New England (Offsite-box 174, Box 85)
  - Art Collections by geographic area, the South (Offsite-box 174, Box 86)
  - Art Collections by geographic area, Rhode Island (Offsite-box 174, Box 87)
  - Art Collections by geographic area, Rhode Island and Massachusetts (Offsite-box 175, Box 88)
  - Art Collections by geographic area, Lexington and Concord (Offsite-box 175, Box 89)
  - Art Collections by geographic area, Lexington and Concord (Offsite-box 175, Box 90)
  - Art Collections by geographic area, Connecticut (Offsite-box 176, Box 91)
  - Art Collections by geographic area, Connecticut (Offsite-box 176, Box 93)
  - Artists, Ezra Ames, 1940-1947 (Offsite-box 183, Box 110)
  - Artists, John Blackburn, 1940-1947 (Offsite-box 132)
  - Artists, John Singleton Copley, 1940-1947 (Offsite-box 132)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 147, Box 7)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 147, Box 8)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 147, Box 9)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 148, Box 10)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 148, Box 11)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 148, Box 12)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 149, Box 13)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 149, Box 14)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 149, Box 15)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 150, Box 16)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 150, Box 17)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 150, Box 18)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 151, Box 19)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 151, Box 20)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 151, Box 21)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 152, Box 22)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 152, Box 23)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 152, Box 24)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 153, Box 25)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 153, Box 26)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 153, Box 27)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 154, Box 28)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 154, Box 29)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 154, Box 30)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 155, Box 31)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 155, Box 32)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 155, Box 33)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 156, Box 34)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 156, Box 35)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 156, Box 36)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 157, Box 37)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 157, Box 38)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 157, Box 39)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 158, Box 40)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 158, Box 41)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 158, Box 42)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 159, Box 43)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 159, Box 44)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 159, Box 45)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 160, Box 46)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 160, Box 47)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 160, Box 48)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 161, Box 49)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 132)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 133)
  - Artists, Ralph Earl, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 134)
  - Artist, John Johnston, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 168, Box 68)
  - Artist, John Johnston, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 168, Box 69)
  - Artist, John Johnston, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 168, Box 70)
  - Artist, John Johnston, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 169, Box 71)
  - Artist, John Johnston, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 169, Box 72)
  - Artists, Thomas McIlworth, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 169, Box 73)
  - Artists, Thomas McIlworth, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 170, Box 74)
  - Artists, Thomas McIlworth, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 170, Box 75)
  - Artists, Thomas McIlworth, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 170, Box 76)
  - Artists, Thomas McIlworth, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 171, Box 77)
  - Artists, Thomas McIlworth, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 171, Box 78)
  - Artists, Thomas McIlworth, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 171, Box 79)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 161, Box 50)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 161, Box 51)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 162, Box 52)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 162, Box 53)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 162, Box 54)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 163, Box 55)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 163, Box 56)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 163, Box 57)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 164, Box 58)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 164, Box 59)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 164, Box 60)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 165, Box 61)
  - Artists, Reuben Moulthrop, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 165, Box 62)
  - Artists, Joseph Steward, 1940-1947 (Offsite-box 173, Box 84)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1940 (Offsite-box 178, Box 99)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1940 (Offsite-box 179, Box 100)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 179, Box 101)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 179, Box 102)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 180, Box 103)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 180, Box 104)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 180, Box 105)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 181, Box 106)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 181, Box 107)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 182, Box 108)
  - Artists, Gilbert Stuart, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 182, Box 109)
  - Artists, John Watson, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 172, Box 81)
  - Artists, John Watson, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 173, Box 82)
  - Artists, John Watson, 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 173, Box 83)
  - Artists A-B, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 113)
  - Artists C-E, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 114)
  - Artists F-Hicks, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 115)
  - Artists Highmore-J, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 116)
  - Artists K-Paul, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 117)
  - Artists Peale, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 118)
  - Artists Pel-Pratt, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 119)
  - Artists R-S, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 120)
  - Artists T-Watson, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 121)
  - Artists West-Z, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 122)
  - Artists, Miniatures, A-N, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 123)
  - Artists, Miniatures, O-Z, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 124)
  - Artists, English Period, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 145, Box 1)
  - Artists, English Period, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 145, Box 2)
  - Artists, English Period, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 145, Box 3)
  - Artists, English Period, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 146, Box 4)
  - Artists, English Period, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 146, Box 5)
  - Artists, English Period, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 146, Box 6)
  - Artists, English and French Painters and Engravers, 1930-1942 (Offsite-box 177, Box 94)
  - Artists, European, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 132)
  - Subjects of Portraits, A-Z, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 125)
  - Subjects of Portraits, Benjamin Franklin, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 126)
  - Subjects of Portraits, George Washington, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 178, Box 98)
  - Subjects of Portraits, George Washington, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 127)
  - Subjects of Portraits, George Washington, 1930-1947 (Offsite-box 128)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1929-1975
  This series contains Sawitzky's corrspondence with librarians, art dealers, museum curators, colleagues, editors, publishers and others.
  - Correspondence A-M, 1933-1944 (Offsite-box 129)
  - Correspondence N-Z, 1929-1975 (Offsite-box 130)
  - Correspondence, for follow-up, 1937-1943 (Offsite-box 131)
  - Correspondence, various, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 132)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1960 (Offsite-box 132)
- Series IV: Published Volumes, 1926-1947
  This series consists of published works, such as books and periodicals, that belonged to William Sawitzky. Many contain his handwritten annotations.
  - Gilbert Stuart: an illustrated descriptive list of his works, by Lawrence Park. Volumes I and II., 1926 (Offsite-box 136)
  - Gilbert Stuart: an illustrated descriptive list of his works, by Lawrence Park. Volumes III and IV., 1926 (Offsite-box 137)
  - Periodicals, 1935-1945 (Offsite-box 138)
    includes various issues of Art News, The Magazine Antiques, and the New-York Historical Society Quarterly.
- Series V: Miscellaneous, 1929-1975
  This series contains items, including notes, photocopies, and photographs, that were previously labelled "miscellaneous."
  - Miscellaneous, 1929-1975 (Offsite-box 139)
  - Miscellaneous, 1929-1975 (Offsite-box 140)
  - Oversize Miscellaneous, 1929-1975 (Offsite-box 141)
  - Oversize Miscellaneous, 1929-1975 (Offsite-box 142)